Northbridge, Mass. Centre Congregational Church records, 1782-2011.
Congregational Library & Archives
Northbridge, Mass. Centre Congregational Church records, 1782-2011.
RG5030
Congregational Library & Archives
3.45 Cubic Feet
(4 boxes)
The town of Northbridge, Massachusetts, was incorporated in 1772 and the First Church in Northbridge was established in 1782. The first meeting house was constructed in 1774. In 1834 a significant portion of the congregation withdrew to form the Congregational Church of Whitinsville (now the Village Congregational Church). The second meeting house was constructed in 1836. In 1879 another contingent of the church's members withdrew to form the Rockdale Congregational Church, though both churches shared a minister until 1897. Around the turn of the century the name for the First Congregational Church in Northbridge was changed to Centre Congregational Church. The second meeting house was destroyed by a fire on February 12, 1932. The Centre Congregational Church joined the United Church of Christ in the early 1960s. The church dissolved in 2011. This collection contains the administrative, financial, and visual records of the Northbridge Centre Congregational Church and its auxiliary organizations.
Centre Congregational Church (Northbridge, Mass.)
First Congregational Church (Northbridge, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives, October 2011, by the Northbridge Centre Congregational Church; no accession number.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Historical Note
The town of Northbridge, Massachusetts, was incorporated in 1772 out of lands which had previously been a part of Mendon and then later Uxbridge. In 1773 the town voted to begin construction on a meeting house and in 1774 construction on the first meeting house was completed. Due, at least in part, to the American Revolutionary War, no Congregational church was formally gathered until 1782. The First Congregational Church in Northbridge was established on June 6, 1782 and John Crane was ordained as the first minister on June 25, 1783. Rev. Crane served as pastor of the church until 1832.
In 1833 the First Congregational Church established a Sunday school. In 1834 a significant portion of the congregation from the southern section of Northbridge, known as Whitinsville, withdrew to form the Congregational Church of Whitinsville (now the Village Congregational Church). In 1835 the first meeting house was demolished and construction on the second meeting house was completed the following year. In 1879 another contingent of the church's members withdrew to form the Rockdale Congregational Church. Both churches were served by the same pastor until 1897 and both churches remained closely united throughout their histories. In 1885 the Ladies Auxiliary group was founded; this organization was later renamed the Ladies Aid Society.
Around the turn of the century the name for the First Congregational Church in Northbridge was changed to Centre Congregational Church. In 1922 the church rejected a proposal, put forth by the Massachusetts Home Missionary Society, for the Centre Congregational Church to merge with the Rockdale Congregational Church. The second meeting house was destroyed by a fire on February 12, 1932. After the fire, the Centre Congregational Church worked closely with the Rockdale Congregational Church and shared a pastor; this formal relationship lasted until 1952. Construction on the third, and final, meeting house was completed in 1836 and the building was dedicated on October 22, 1836. In 1940 the Church Society was officially dissolved and Centre Congregational Church was formally incorporated. In 1952 Rev. Clayton H. Witt resigned from Centre Congregational Church but not from the Rockdale Congregational Church; the formal relationship between the two churches was officially ended shortly after Rev. Witt's resignation.
The Centre Congregational Church joined the United Church of Christ in the early 1960s. In 2011 the Centre Congregational Church dissolved, following financial difficulties, and was absorbed by the Rockdale Congregational Church.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the administrative, financial, and visual records of the Northbridge Centre Congregational Church. Included within this collection are the records of the church and parish, guest books, membership lists, financial records, collection records, extensive records from the Ladies Aid Society, and photographs.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the four series listed below. Within each series, materials have been primarilly arranged in chronological order by start date. Materials that are very closely related, by either subject matter or a temporal connection, have been grouped together.
Series 1: Church and society records, 1782-2011
Series 2: Financial records, 1815-2011
Series 3: Clubs and organizations, 1909-1998
Series 4: Visual materials, 1869-2002
Technical Requirements
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
Bibliography
Hackett, Peter. Manual and History of the Centre Congregational Church, Northbridge, Mass. Northbridge: 1962.
Church bells.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Guest books.; Music in churches.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Sunday school teachers -- Photographs.; Sunday schools -- Photographs.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Centre Congregational Church (Northbridge, Mass.); First Congregational Church (Northbridge, Mass.); Northbridge (Mass.) -- Church history.
- Church and society records, 1782 2011; 1782-2011; 26 Files; (11 volumes, 15 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the administrative and important membership records of the Centre Congregational Church and the Church Society. Included in the series are administrative record books, important publications, correspondence, records related to anniversaries, newsletters and programs, guest books, and membership records.
  - Church records, 1782 1836; 1782-1836 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Church records, 1835 1904; 1835-1904 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Church records, 1905 1982; 1905-1982 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Church records, 1952 1982; 1952-1982 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Church records, 1982 2000; 1982-2000 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Society records, 1814 1908; 1814-1908 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Society records, 1910 1940; 1910-1940 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Confessions of Faith, 1833 1867; 1833, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters of dismission, 1891 1911; 1891-1911 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Church manual, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Church attendance records, 1940 1950; 1940-1950 (Box 3, Volume 19)
  - Guest book, 1952 1982; 1952-1982 (Box 3, Volume 14)
  - Guest book, 1982 2007; 1982-2007 (Box 3, Volume 15)
  - Dissolvement of Rockdale and Centre Congregational Churches partnership, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - List of officers and committees, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Membership list, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Church manual and history, 1962 (Box 3, Volume 17)
  - Ushers' report cards, 1967 1979; 1967-1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bicentennial records, 1981 1982; 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Rev. Gordon C. Merten program notes, 1981 1983; 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Village Congregational Church 150th Anniversary, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Separated Materials
    These materials were removed from the Church records, 1952-1982.
  - Organ rededication concert, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Centre Church brochures, 1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Member directory, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Newsletters, 2006 2009; 2006-2009 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters, 2009 2011; 2009-2011 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 225th anniversary service, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Financial records, 1815 2011; 1815-2011; 22 Files; (17 volumes, 5 folders)
  This series contains the financial records of the Centre Congregational Church and Society. Included within the records are extensive accounts of collections taken during each Sunday service.
  - Treasurer's book, 1815 1897; 1815-1897 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Society account book, 1815 1913; 1815-1913 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Church treasury account book, 1835 1876; 1835-1876 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Church treasury account book, 1840 1901; 1840-1901 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Treasurer's book, 1897 1927; 1897-1927 (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - Account book, 1945 1950; 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Collection records, 1946 1950; 1946-1950 (Box 2, Volume 5)
  - Collection records, 1950 1953; 1950-1953 (Box 2, Volume 6)
  - Collection records, 1954 1957; 1954-1957 (Box 2, Volume 7)
  - Collection records, 1958 1961; 1958-1961 (Box 2, Volume 8)
  - Collection records, 1962 1965; 1962-1965 (Box 2, Volume 9)
  - Collection records, 1966 1969; 1966-1969 (Box 2, Volume 10)
  - Collection records, 1970 1973; 1970-1973 (Box 2, Volume 11)
  - Collection records, 1974 1977; 1974-1977 (Box 2, Volume 12)
  - Collection records, 1978 1981; 1978-1981 (Box 2, Volume 13)
  - Collection records, 1983 1986; 1983-1986 (Box 2, Volume 14)
  - Collection records, 1988 1991; 1988-1991 (Box 2, Volume 15)
  - Collection records, 1993 1997; 1993-1997 (Box 2, Volume 16)
  - Collection records, 2003 2005; 2003-2005 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Collection records, 2006 2007; 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Collection records, 2008 2009; 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Collection records, 2010 2011; 2010-2011 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Clubs and organizations, 1909 1998; 1909-1998; 23 Files; (19 volumes, 4 folders)
  This series contains records related to the various clubs and organizations that were administered by members of the Centre Congregational Church. The majority of this series is records related to the Ladies Aid Society which was active throughout the twentieth-century. Also included in the series are records related to Christian Endeavor and the Community Association.
  - Ladies Aid Society records, 1909 1925; 1909-1925 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Ladies Aid Society records, 1925 1938; 1925-1938 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Ladies Aid Society records, 1938 1942; 1938-1942 (Box 3, Volume 3)
  - Ladies Aid Society records, 1941 1952; 1941-1952 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Ladies Aid Society records, 1943 1950; 1943-1950 (Box 3, Volume 5)
  - Ladies Aid Society records, 1950 1958; 1950-1958 (Box 3, Volume 6)
  - Ladies Aid Society records, 1952 1959; 1952-1959 (Box 3, Volume 7)
  - Ladies Aid Society records, 1958 1965; 1958-1965 (Box 3, Volume 8)
  - Ladies Aid Society records, 1965 1971; 1965-1971 (Box 3, Volume 9)
  - Ladies Aid Society records, 1971 1985; 1971-1985 (Box 3, Volume 10)
  - Ladies Aid Society treasurer's book, 1912 1930; 1912-1930 (Box 2, Volume 17)
  - Ladies Aid Society treasurer's book, 1922 1934; 1922-1934 (Box 2, Volume 18)
  - Ladies Aid Society treasurer's book, 1929 1948; 1929-1948 (Box 2, Volume 19)
  - Ladies Aid Society treasurer's book, 1951 1977; 1951-1977 (Box 2, Volume 20)
  - Ladies Aid Society treasurer's book, 1984 1998; 1984-1998 (Box 2, Volume 21)
  - Ladies Aid Society club membership, 1931 1933; 1931-1933 (Box 3, Volume 11)
  - Ladies Aid Society president's notes, 1959 1969; 1959-1969 (Box 3, Volume 12)
  - Ladies Aid Society president's notes, 1969 1971; 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ladies Aid Society constitution and by-laws, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    These materials were removed from the Ladies Aid treasurer's book, 1929-1948.
  - Christian Endeavor treasurer's book, 1909 1921; 1909-1921 (Box 3, Volume 13)
  - Christian Endeavor booklets, 1910 1931; 1910, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Worcester South Christian Endeavor Union correspondence, 1932 1933; 1932-1933 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    These materials were removed from the Christian Endeavor treasurer's book, 1909-1921.
  - Community Association financial records, 1955 1964; 1955-1964 (Box 3, Volume 16)
- Visual materials, 1869 2002; 1869-2002; 17 Files; (1 volume, 16 folders)
  This series contains visual materials related to the church and its members. Especially prominent are photographs of Sunday School students and teachers. Most of the materials are photographs, though the series also contains postcards and a physical piece of the church's old bell.
  - Choir photograph album, 1869 (Box 3, Volume 18)
  - Rev. James H. Childs, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Susan B. Childs, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sunday School class and teachers, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Inside Northbridge Centre Church, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Four boys, circa 1935 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Choir members, circa 1940 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - First meeting house site, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Postcards, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Tavern house, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Second meeting house, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Baby Thatcher, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Sunday School students and teachers, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sunday School students and teacher, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Piece of old church bell, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)